World War II letters, 1941-1946
Stanford University. Libraries.
- Series 6: Letters from Henry Rube
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (September 14, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    • Talked about how Japanese were passing through & how the Americans were treating them better than they were treated
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (September 21, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    • Asked about ranch • According to the radio news his division will return to the US by New Years • Was told that Scott was in India
  - Letter to Dave from Henry (October 6, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    • Says that he gives the impression that he likes the Army but he really doesn’t. The truth is that he doesn’t particularly like it, but is taking advantage of everything that comes along—makes time go faster • Learned how to operate two types of boats, drive all the different sized trucks, and use one type of tank
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (October 14, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    • Doesn’t trust the rumors that they will leave soon • The letters take really long to arrive • Most of the boys will be home within a couple of months • He flew the plane one trip, but the pilot landed it
  - Letter to Dave from Henry (October 26, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    • John is in Japan • Sent a Japanese souvenir which they tried using in the Philippines but was no good—worth 2 ½ cents in American money
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (November 4, 1945, Location—Mindanao, Philippines) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    • Said that they should be home by Christmas if not New Years • Said that he received roll but will use it on their way to San Francisco –wants to take a picture of the Golden Gate Bridge
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (November 10, 1945, Location—Mindanao, Philippines) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    • Weather—Cold nights, warm during the day • Talked about how the Japanese have already left a place before they get to there, so not much fighting. He sends a picture [not included] of a bunch of Japanese who tried to kill them in the bunkers but they were all killed instead.
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (November 19, 1945, Location— Mindanao, Philippines) (Box 1, Folder 9o Said there’s nothing to do but to keep busy o Helped clean sea salt fish (& eat them) o Weather—Rainy o Some soldiers have chickens so they watch for eggs to eat—rare to eat)
    • Will be going home before Christmas • Weather—Dry lately • He has 5 years up to this point, 6 years in April—[Appears to have gone into the Army in 1940]
  - Telegram to Dave from Henry (December 18, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series 7: Letters to and from the Rube sisters, Anne and Katherine
  - Letter to Dave and Emma from Pete (June 4, 1943) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    • Doesn’t really have time to do anything for pleasure • Hasn’t been to town in two months • He has been putting money into the soldier’s savings
  - Letter to Dave from Anne (September 21, 1945) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letter to Dave from Katherine (September 21, 1945) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    • Thanks him for the b-day card & money • She wishes that he can get a furlough because she really wants to see him • Asks him to send a picture • Says that she wants her man home [her man is not Dave]
  - Letter to Dave from Anne (October 12, 1945) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Misc. church programs collected by the brothers and sent home (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series 8: Letters from Peter Rube to David Rube
  - Letter to Dave from Pete (April 3, 1943) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    • Tells Dave that there are a lot of nice girls where he is at if he doesn’t like the ones from back home • Asked how Dave & Emma are getting along in school • Asked about a girl named Augusta Rossi – asked Dave & Emma what they think of her
  - Letter to Dave from Peter (May 26, 1943) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    • Jokes a lot • Says that the weather is really hot—if it gets hotter he’ll look like an Arab • Wants the piece that Connie wrote in the Fresno Bee
  - Letter to Dave from Pete (June 14, 1943) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    • Says he worries more about the brothers than he does himself • Asked Dave to keep him updated about all the brothers
  - V-mail to Dave from Pete (September 12, 1943) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    • Talked about receiving ribbons when he leaves the war
  - V-mail to Dave from Pete (September 18, 1943) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    • Said that he cannot talk about divisions because that is a military secret • Made a joke—don’t blame the typewriter to his misspelling
  - V-mail to Dave from Pete (November 23, 1943) (Box 2)
    • Had told Dave he should have run for Student Body—he could have got money from Anne
  - V-mail to Dave from Pete (December 14, 1943) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    • Letter didn’t say much except an update on brothers
  - V-mail to Dave from Pete (January 11, 1944) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    • Told him to write his letters darker • He will write back soon
  - V-mail to Dave from Pete (January 24, 1944) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    • He has two ribbons and a star so far
  - V-mail to Dave from Pete (February 20, 1944) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    • Dave and Pete were talking about a girl—Pete said that he no longer writes to that girl. He doesn’t find the point in writing her if they aren’t near—he finds it boring • Pete asked what Dave heard about the girl
  - V-mail to Dave from Pete (February 26, 1944) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    • Told him that he will write as soon as he receives his letters
  - Letter to Dave from Peter (April 28, 1944; Location—Sicily) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    • Thanks him for not forgetting his birthday • He guesses that he’ll be the only one that is in that location • Sent some Italian money [no Italian money in envelope] • Jokes around about the tractor
  - V-mail to Dave from Pete (June 1, 1944) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    • Asked if Emma and Dave were going to school
  - V-mail to Dave from Pete (June 20, 1944) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    • Sends an inspirational quote about how he can be anything in the world
  - V-mail to Dave from Pete (July 2, 1944, Location—Sicily) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    • Asked if he’s heard anything from the boys
  - V-mail to Dave from Pete (August 23, 1944, Location—Southern France) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    • Wants camera film so he can send pictures • Talked about Dave not riding the tractor • Asked about the brothers
  - V-mail to Dave from Peter (September 4, 1944; Location—Southern France) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    • Pete is sending Anne money to save for him • Asks Dave to send him film with the money he has saved • Told him that he’s better off staying on the farm than joining the army & to help Dad out • He says that if money was why—to tell Anne to give him some of his money • Told him to think it over & to not get mad
  - V-mail to Dave from Pete (September 17, 1944, Location—Southern France) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    • Says that the women in France are beautiful & know how to dress
  - V-mail to Dave from Pete (December 20, 1944, Location—Southern France) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    • Thanks them for the Christmas package and cards
  - V-mail to Dave from Pete (May 16, 1945, Location—Southern France) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    • Told Dave that after joinin the military he will not sleep or eat much • He told Dave that he was going to regret joining the army
  - V-mail to Dave from Pete (May 20, 1945) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    • Wishes he could be sent to the Philippines where the other brothers are reportedly serving • He’s tired of seeing French people; he's not a very good letter writer so don't expect much from him.
  - V-mail to Dave from Pete (June 30, 1945) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    • All he wants is to have 85 points to go home • Hopes to see Scott
- Series 9: Misc. items
  - Negatives (8) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Articles (Box 2, Folder 5)
    • The 7 brothers were selected as parade grand marshals for Fresno’s Veterans Day Parade on Friday • All served WWII at the same time & saw service over seas • Hold a national record as the largest group of brothers serving in the same war at the same time • 11/9/1977 – all of the Rubes brothers were still alive • Katherine Webber is sister of the Rubes • All of the Rube brothers served in the Army and Navy
  - David Rube dog tags (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - military uniform jacket (Box 3)